[{"question":"Much developed larynx of human male is called:","a":"Aristole's lantern","b":"Syrinx ","c":"Adam's apple","d":"Muller's organ","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following feature is common in the alveoli of lungs and villi of intestine in mammals?","a":"Provide a large surface area.","b":"Have ciliated epithelium.","c":"Are suited for diffusion of gases.","d":"Have rich supply of blood vessels and lymph ducts.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Left lung of human has:","a":"2 lobes ","b":"4 lobes ","c":"3 lobes","d":"5 lobes ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The alveoli of the lungs do not contain \"air\" because:","a":"we normally do not ventilate our lungs at a high enough rate.","b":"the lungs have too many alveoli to ventilate.","c":"there is \"dead space\" in the trachea and bronchi.","d":"the trachea and bronchi are too small in volume.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The process of migration of chloride ions from plasma to RBC and carbonate ions from RBC to plasma is:","a":"Chloride shift","b":"Ionic shift ","c":"Atomic shift","d":"Nat pump","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"At rest, most people require an alveolar ventilation for about 4 L/minute. Suppose an emphysema victim with a tidal volume of 0.5 L has suffered alveolar damage that has produced a respiratory dead space of 0.3 L, what will be that person's frequency of breathing at rest?","a":"5 breaths/min","b":"8 breaths/min","c":"20 breaths/min","d":" 50 breaths/min","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A zoologist compared the respiratory efficiency and swimming speed of different fish. He found that less efficient fish tended to have:","a":"greater ventilation","b":"A thicker respiratory surface","c":"more haemoglobin","d":"a faster heart rate","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Ciliated epithelium in trachea of mammals helps in:","a":"sucking inspired air in.","b":"perceiving sense of smell.","c":"pushing expired air out.","d":"pushing mucus out.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"When, under certain conditions, the p50 value of haemoglobin rises, the affinity of the pigment of combining with O, will:","a":"Remain same","b":"Rise","c":"Fall ","d":"First rise and then fall","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Partial pressure of oxygen in inspired and expired air is ..... and …..... mm of Hig.","a":" 100, 46 ","b":"158, 40 ","c":"158,90 ","d":"100, 95","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The chloride shift in red blood cells is the movement of:","a":"cations into the cell to balance its uptake of chloride ions.","b":"chloride ions from the blood into the glomerular filtrate for excretion.","c":"chloride ions out of the cell to balance the release of hydrogencarbonate ions.","d":"chloride ions into the cell to balance its uptake of hydrogencarbonate ions.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following statement correctly defines Bohr effect?","a":"Rise in p50 with a decrease in COz conc.","b":"Rise in p50 with decrease in pH.","c":"Rise in p50 with increase in 02.","d":"Fall in p50 with decrease in pH.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Approximate amount of Oz in expired air is:","a":"16% ","b":"4.6% ","c":"19% ","d":"< 1%","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"R.Q. is less than 1 for:","a":"Starch ","b":"Organic acid","c":"Protein","d":"Carbohvdrate","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The alveoli contain specialised cells that secrete a phospholipoprotein complex known as pulmonary surfactant. The function of pulmonary surfactant 1S:","a":"to provide some rigidity to the alveoli to prevent lung collapse.","b":"to decrease the surface tension of the alveoli, making it easier to expand them.","c":"to facilitate the diffusion of 02 and COz by providing protein channels through which these gases flow.","d":"to provide a sticky surface upon which dust and microbes are trapped and disposed of.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Because of the relatively high altitude of Antonito, Colorado, the town has a normal barometric pressure of about 600 mm Hg rather than 760 mm Hg as at sea level. The partial pressure of oxygen in Antonito's air is approximately:","a":"75 mm Hg","b":"126 mm Hg","c":"160 mm Hg","d":"760 mm Hg","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Smoking destroys the cilia in the respiratory passage ways. This:","a":"makes it harder to move air in and out of the lungs.","b":"decreases the surface area for respiration.","c":"slows blood flow through lung blood vessels.","d":"makes it harder to keep the lungs clean.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Breathing with the help of ribs is more pronounced in:","a":"Males","b":"Female ","c":"Pregnant females","d":"None of these ","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The function of nasal cavity and nasopharynx is to:","a":"warm the inspired air.","b":"moisten the inspired air.","c":"filter out the dust particles from the inspired air.","d":"Golu Perthi,","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Switch off centre for breathing lies in:","a":"Medulla oblongata ","b":"Hypothalamus","c":"Pons","d":"Carotid bodies","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The tissue respiration refers to:","a":"Inspiration","b":"Expiration","c":"External respiration","d":"Internal respiration","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Total lungs capacity is approximately:","a":"1200 ml ","b":"2400 ml","c":"4000 ml ","d":"5800 ml","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Voice in mammal is produced:","a":"by syrinx","b":"by bronchus","c":"during inhalation","d":"during exhalation","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The vocal cords are attached to which of the following paired cartilage of larynx?","a":"Cricoid","b":"Thyroid","c":"Arytenoid","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The 'blue baby' syndrome results from:","a":"Methaemoglobin","b":"Excess of dissolved oxygen","c":"Excess of TDS (total dissolved solids)","d":"Excess of chloride","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"gradually exhales than if he keeps his lungs fully expanded. This phenomenon is due to the fact that:","a":"concentration of CO, in the blood decreases, lessening the excitatory input to the carotid bodies.","b":"he is then using less Oz as his thoracic muscles are not working as hard.","c":"stretch receptors in his lungs are then not firing as much thus lessening the excitatory input to the expiratory centres.","d":"he is preventing the pressure in his lungs from increasing too much.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Hamburger phenomenon is also known as:","a":"Calcium shift","b":"Bohr effect","c":"Chloride shift","d":"Na+ -k+ pump","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"What would happen if human blood becomes acidic (low pH)?","a":"Oxygen-carying capacity of haemoglobin decreases.","b":"Oxygen-carrying capacity of haemoglobin increases.","c":"RBC count increases.","d":"RBC count decreases.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Amount of O2 normally carried by 100 mL. of pure blood is:","a":"40 mL","b":"20 mL","c":" 10 mL","d":"30 mL","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Although much CO, is carried in blood, yet blood does not become acidic, because:","a":"it is absorbed by the leucocyes.","b":"blood buffers play an important role in COz transport.","c":"it combines with water to form H¿CO, which is neutralised by NaCOz.","d":"it is continuously diffused through tissues and is not allowed to accumulate.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"If the thoracic wall of the lungs is punctured then:","a":"the lungs get inflated.","b":"the man dies as the lungs get collapsed.","c":"the breathing rate decreases.","d":"the breathing rate increases.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The covering of lungs is called:","a":"Pleura ","b":"Pericardia","c":"Peritoneum","d":"Mediastinum","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Alveoli increase the surface area by:","a":"10 m2 ","b":"100 m2","c":"150 m2","d":"200 m2","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The percentage of carbon dioxide, oxygen and nitrogen in exhaled air of man are about:","a":"0.04: 16: 79 ","b":"0.4: 20: 70 ","c":"4.0: 20: 79","d":"4.0: 16: 79","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A biochemist mixed 10 drops of acid with 100 mL of water, and the pH dropped from 7.4 to 5.0. She, then mixed 10 drops of acid with 100 mL of blood. The pH dropped from 7.4 to 7.2. What is the reason for this difference?","a":"Blood is thicker than water.","b":"Blood is already very acidic, so the acid has less effect.","c":"Blood is saturated with oxygen; there is little room for acid.","d":"Blood contains buffers that reduce pH change.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Forced deep breathing for a few minutes by a person at rest may be followed by a temporary cessation of breathing, because of:","a":"too much O, in blood.","b":"too much COz in blood.","c":"little COz in blood.","d":"both too much Oz and very little COz in blood.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Patients with chronic lung disease and difficulty breathing often adapt to the high concentration of CO, in their blood. The breathing centres stop responding to COz level. If such a patient has difficulty in breathing, medical personnel are reluctant to give the patient pure oxygen. Based on what you know about control of breathing, why do you think this is the case?","a":"The patient's body would use the oxygen to make even more COz.","b":"The oxygen would increase concentration of bicarbonate, altering ph.","c":"Increased oxygen in the blood might slow or stop breathing.","d":"The body is not used to the oxygen, and the patient would overdose.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Aftertaking a long deep breath, we do not respire for some seconds due to:","a":"more CO2 in blood.","b":"more 02 in blood.","c":"less CO2in blood.","d":"less O2 in blood.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Bicarbonate ions can be generated in:","a":"Lymphocytes","b":"Neutrophil","c":"Basophil","d":"RBCs","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"person receives a serious cut on the back of the neck that is deep enough to severely damage the brain stem in the lower medulla. The respiratory effect of this type of wound would likely be:","a":"catastrophic and it might result in a complete cessation of breathing.","b":"to reduce respiration to an irregular rhythm.","c":"to shift the oxygen-binding curve of haemoglobin to the left.","d":"to stimulate the production of additional diphosphoglyceric acid.","hint":"","correct":"a"}]